Alexander N. Charters Papers
Alexander N. Charters Papers
- Writings
  - Writings by others
    - Charters, Margaret / ISCEA reports, 1993; 1998 (Box 247)
    - Charters, Margaret / Methods of comparative andragogy, 1995; International Expert Seminar for ISCAE (Box 247)
    - Chmaj, Deborah R. and Wolde, Menbere / The Laubach Collection: Personal Papers of Frank C. Laubach, Documents of Laubach Literacy Inc., abridged version [Frost ID: ANC 56], 1974; foreword by Charters (Box 247)
    - Chmaj, Deborah R. and Wolde, Menbere / The Laubach Collection: Personal Papers of Frank C. Laubach, Documents of Laubach Literacy Inc. [Frost ID: ANC 57], 1974; foreword by Charters (Box 247)
    - Committee for Continuing Education Directory [Frost ID: NPU 24], 1970-1971 (Box 247)
    - Conger, D. Stuart / Canadian open learning systems, photocopy of Chapter 2 from unidentified book (Box 247)
    - Cornanicova, Kozalia / Juraj Fandly and Samuel Tesedik: Influential Slovak adult educationalists [sic] of the 18th c., undated (Box 247)
    - Cushing, Richard G. / Radio is alive and well, 1970; speech given at Syracuse University (Box 247)
    - DeCrow, Ironside, Vaughn / Adult education information services: Establishment of a prototype system, 1967 (Box 247)
    - DeCrow, Ironside, Vaughn / Directory of adult education associations [Frost ID: ANC 15], 1966 (Box 247)
    - Dede, Chris / Beyond the information superhighway, undated (Box 247)
    - Dees, Norman and Parsons, David / Teachers and taught, circa 1970; published by University of Glasgow; signed by the authors (Box 247)
    - Drazek, Stanley / Continuing education: Its past and future, 1978 (Box 247)
    - Dupont, Christian / Bringing Dante to America, 2003 (Box 247)
    - Eckstein, Max and Noah, Harold J. / Forms and functions of secondary school leaving examinations: International variations, 1988 (Box 247)
    - Engel, David / Pedagogy in higher education: Notes on the continuing education of a theology faculty, 1964; published by the Christian Faith and Higher Education Institute (Box 247)
    - Felkai, Laszlo / Baron József Eötvös und die Erwachsenenbildung, undated (Box 247)
    - Frost, Jane B. / Historical and research materials related to adult and continuing education, 1988; comprehensive bibliography of Charters' writings, including documents written by others at his request. Published by SUPCE as MSS 33. (Box 226)
      For later edition see Historical and research materials related to adult and continuing education, 1992 at the beginning of the Writings series, or see
      related collection SUPCE: MSS 35
    - Geyer, Caroline / Dr. Jessie A. Charters: Reclaiming her role in adult education, 1980; PhD student's paper on Dr. Charters, 14 pp. (Box 247)
    - Gilliland, Richard / Some thoughts on the nature and importance of adult education for the 21st century, circa 1998 (Box 247)
    - Glennon, Vincent J. / Research needs in elementary school mathematics education, 1966; reprint from The Arithmetic Teacher (Box 247)
    - Goldberg, Maxwell H. / The impact of technological change on the humanities, 1965; reprint from The Educational Record (Box 247)
    - Goldman, Samuel / The school system and its social problems, 1968; presented at Chief School Administrators Conference, Minnowbrook (Box 247)
    - Goode, Malvin R. / A change of climate, 1967; presented at Onondaga Urban League annual dinner (Box 247)
    - Gruen, William / A pragmatic criticism of community-centered adult education, 1955; reprint from Adult Education (Box 247)
    - Henderson, Mary L. / Education periodicals and serials in Syracuse University Libraries, 1971 (Box 248)
    - Holland, Kenneth G. / Education in a world of increasing knowledge, 1965; speech, Howard University (Box 248)
    - Houle, Cyril O. / He, 1970; Chicago Literary Club, Club Paper LXVIII (Box 248)
    - Jensen, Liveright, Hallenbeck (ed.s) / Adult education: Outlines of an emerging field of university study, 1964; published monograph, with Charters' margin notes and highlighting (Box 248)
    - Jug, Jurij / Dr. Franjo Zgec, undated (Box 248)
    - Keenan, Terrance / The right to know, circa 1997 (Box 248)
    - Keenan, Terrance / Salvaging the past, 1996 (Box 248)
    - Kett, Joseph F. / The dissenter in the history of adult education, circa 1990 (Box 248)
    - Kidd, J. Roby / Adult education and the school, circa 1960 (Box 248)
    - Kidd, J. Roby / Comparative adult education: Some question or problems to be considered, 1977 (Box 248)
    - Kidd, J. Roby / Note on comparative adult education, 1980 (Box 248)
    - Kidd, J. Roby / People learning from each other, 1953 (Box 248)
    - Kidd, J. Roby / Putting words to work, circa 1955 (Box 248)
    - King, Patricia / Hey, why don't we start an external high school diploma program?, 1993; published in Syracuse University Courier, Vol. XXVII, No. 1 (Box 248)
    - Kulich, Jindra / Recent publications in comparative study of adult education, 1990 (Box 248)
    - Kulich, Jindra / Trial world bibliography on international comparative adult education 1945-1995, 1996; compiled at request of ISCAE (Box 248)
    - Lavrnja, Ilija and Klapan, Anita / The originality and topicality of Dr. Jure Turic's reflections on adult education, 1996; presented at 6th International Conference on History of Adult Education (Box 248)
    - Leagans, J. Paul / multiple, Communication process in rural development; A concept of needs; Continuing education: A fourth dimension; Developing professional leadership in extension education; Extension education and agricultural modernization; Guides to extension teaching in developing countries; also includes resume (Box 248)
    - Lowe, John / Education and European integration, 1992; reprint from International Review of Education, Vol. 38, No. 6 (Box 248)
    - McGrath, Earl J. / Adult education research for a changing world, 1965 (Box 248)
    - Mocker, Donald W. and George E. Spear / Lifelong learning: Formal, nonformal, informal, and self-directed, 1982 (Box 248)
    - Ndlovu, Sikhanyiso D. / [untitled], undated (Box 248)
    - Nordic Documentation Center for Mass Communication Research, Aarhus (Denmark) / Mass communication researchers in Scandinavia, 1978; microfiche; 2 copies (Box 248)
    - Polturzycki, Jozef / Changes and development of Polish adult education in XXth century, undated (Box 248)
    - Pont, Anthony Michael / Comparative international adult education: Product vs process, circa 1982 (Box 248)
    - Rawlings, Lyngrid / Participatory research: A vehicle for people empowerment, 1983 (Box 248)
    - Samolovcev, Borivoj / Adult education as a function of leisure, 1971 (Box 248)
    - Schouten, G. H. L. / Survey of adult education in Europe, 1974; Council of Europe course description (Box 248)
    - Selman, Gordon / Chronology of adult education in British Columbia, 1977 (Box 248)
    - Serse, Alexandra / History of adult education in Slovenia in the period 1750-1850, undated (Box 248)
    - Shepard, Warren / Hoisting the engineer with his own petard, 1956; reprint from Shakespeare Quarterly, Vol VII, No. 2 (Box 248)
    - Siddiqui, Dilnawaz / Contributions of Alexander N. Charters to the field of adult education (20pp), 1996 (Box 249)
    - Siddiqui, Dilnawaz / Contributions of Alexander N. Charters to the field of adult education (46pp), 1996 (Box 249)
    - Smith, Aker, Kidd / Handbook of Adult Education [Frost ID: ANC 19], 1970; For correspondence and drafts, see Professional: Handbook of Adult Education. A published edition of this book has been sent to cataloging; please refer to to locate this item.
    - Spaulding, Seth / Are scholars in adult education facing a crisis of identity?, 1976 (Box 249)
    - Stubblefield, Harold / Shaping the democratic personality: Paul Bergevin's pedagogy of participation, undated (Box 249)
    - Takatsuka, Satoru and Okamura, Seiichi / New trends in extension education in Japan, 1972 (Box 249)
    - Tough, Allen / Major learning efforts: Recent research and future directions, 1977 (Box 249)
    - Treciokiene, Edita / N.S.F. Grundtvig and M. Valancius, original enlighteners of adults, 1996 (Box 249)
    - Vaughn, Betty Jane / Directory of Adult Education Associations [Frost ID: ANC 8], 1965; Numerous editions of this were produced under various editors. See related collection SUPCE: LCE series, no's 1, 2, 4 and 5.
    - Vaughn, Betty Jane / Directory of Adult Education Associations [Frost ID: MIS 1], 1970; published edition, SUPCE LCE 5 (Box 249)
    - Vaughn, Harold / When Syracuse University established a presence abroad, 2010; published as AIEA 11; 2 copies (Box 249)
    - Vike, James A. / Regional responsiveness to central political influences: Examining variances in OSHA enforcement activities at the regional level, 2004; author is ANC's son-in-law (Box 249)
    - Vike, James A. / State influence in the presidential selection process, undated; Vike is ANC's son-in-law (Box 249)
    - Walter, Jim / Marshall A. Hudson: Pioneer adult religious educator, 1988 (Box 249)
    - Wijetunga, W. M. K. / The status of biographical history and career research in international adult education, undated (Box 249)
    - Wijetunga, W. M. K. / Summary of "Reflections on mainstreaming of adult education into the academic life of Syracuse University 1948-1973", undated; summary of Charters' paper (Box 249)
    - Wilson, David / Elements of a prosopographic and institutional history of comparative education, undated (Box 249)
    - Winters, Clifford L. / Off-campus graduate centers: A problem of university adult education, 1960; reprint from Adult Education, Winter 1960 (Box 249)
    - Ziegler, Christl / Outstanding women in adult education: The exceptional scene of the British and the American zones of occupation in Germany 1945-1949, undated (Box 249)
    - Ziegler, Warren L. / multiple, 1973; draft amendments to the AEA Act; Draft proposal for new legislation; Towards a perspective on the future pf adult education in the United States (Box 249)
    - [unknown] / David Unaipon's contribution to aboriginal higher education, undated (Box 249)
    - [unknown] / Education in Slovenia for the 21st century, undated (Box 249)
    - [unknown] / Futures-invention: A brief description, undated (Box 249)
      See also Syracuse University: School of Education: ATE 621, Futures-Invention: Laboratory in adult teaching.
    - [unknown] / Mandatory continuing education, undated; outline only (Box 249)
    - [unknown] / My pigeon house 1926-1930, undated; typescript; appears to be a memoir (Box 249)
    - [unknown] / University adult education in Taiwan, undated (Box 249)
    - [unknown] / What is UNESCO?, undated; notes for speech (Box 249)
    - [unknown] / miscellaneous unidentified notes (Box 249)
- Memorabilia
  - Activities of Alexander N. Charters, 1985-2002; 2004,; 2006; 8 folders; compiled by ANC at different times; the date on folder is the date the list was compiled, not the date(s) the activities took place; there is extensive duplication (Box 250)
  - Activities related to UNESCO, undated (Box 250)
  - Activities (short list), undated (Box 250)
  - Address lists, personal, 1996-2000; 2002; 2 folders (Box 250)
  - Address lists, personal, 2004; 2009 (Box 251)
  - Address lists, services, 1996; 2000,; 2002 (Box 251)
  - Anniversary, 50th wedding, 2002; Alex and Margaret; text of speech given by son David (Box 251)
  - Awards and certificates
    - Lists of, to 2005, compiled by ANC, the latest dated October 2005; includes some handwritten notes by ANC (Box 251)
    - Department of Education, British Columbia, 1941; teaching certificate (Box 251)
    - Royal Canadian Naval Volunteer Reserve, 1943[?]; commission as Temporary Sub-Lieutenant (Oversize 8)
    - Balliol College, Oxford, 1945; "Lieut. A. N. Charters" certificate of completion for unnamed course; includes souvenir picture postcard (Box 251)
    - Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC), 1960; certificate of recognition for serving as president (Box 251)
    - Order of Equatorial Air Voyagers, 1964; certificate, from the airship "City of Newcastle" (Box 251)
    - University of Toledo Management Development Program, 1965; certificate of completion (Box 251)
    - National University Extension Association (NUEA), 1966; certificate of recognition for serving as president (Box 251)
    - American Airlines, 1967; commission as "Admiral of the Flagship Fleet" (Oversize 8)
    - Japan Air Lines, 1972; certificate for crossing international date line (Box 251)
    - Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC), 1973; certificate of appreciation (Box 251)
    - Wallace Bittner Service Citation, National Association of University Evening Colleges, 1974 (Box 252)
    - Thursday Morning Round Table, Syracuse University, 1975; certificate of appreciation (Box 251)
    - National University Extension Association (NUEA), 1975; certificate of appreciation (Box 251)
    - Syracuse University Chancellor's Group, 1978 (Box 251)
    - Adult Education Association of the United States of American (AEA/USA), 1980; certificate of appreciation for establishment of continuing education library at SU (Box 251)
    - Pioneer Award, Adult Education Association of the United States of American (AEA/USA), 1980; small marble plaque (Box 252)
    - Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE) lifetime membership, 1983 (Box 251)
    - Department of Education, Syracuse University, 1983; plaque listing positions held by ANC; given on occasion of his retirement (Box 252)
    - International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) membership certificates, 1983; 1984,; 1986 (Box 251)
    - William Pearson Tolley Award, Syracuse University, 1986; large medal, boxed; one folder of documentation with letter, photograph (Oversize 1)
      See also Photographs: Tolley Award below
    - FIDEA (Institut International d'Andragogie), 1986; certification of appreciation (Box 251)
    - Syracuse University Kellogg Project, 1988; appreciation plaque (Box 252)
    - International Council for Adult Education (ICAE), 1990; certification of appreciation, printed on fabric scroll (Oversize 1)
    - International Adult and Continuing Education Hall of Fame, 1996; medal, photographs (Box 251)
    - Lifetime Achievement Award, Central New York Council for Adult and Continuing Education (CNY/CACE), 1998; plaque (Box 253)
    - AAA lifetime membership, 1998 (Box 251)
    - Center for Leadership Development, Kiev, 2001; guest lecturer certificate of appreciation (Box 251)
    - Special Commemorative Award, Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE), 2003; glass plaque on wooden base (Oversize 1)
    - Julius M. Nolte Award, University Continuing Education Association, 2004; nomination packet (Box 251)
    - Julius M. Nolte Award, University Continuing Education Association, 2004; engraved glass plaque (Oversize 1)
    - Sam Brightman Award, 2005; pillar with gold cup (Oversize 1)
    - Rotary Club of Syracuse, 2006; plaque recognizing 50 years of membership (Box 253)
    - President's Award, American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE), 2006; plaque recognizing "commitment and dedication" (Box 253)
    - Unidentified plaque, 2008; photo of ANC and text summarizing his service to the field of adult education (Oversize 1)
    - Alpha Lambda Sigma Adult Education Foundation, undated; certificate of recognition (Box 251)
    - Inter-American Society, undated; membership certificate (Box 251)
    - Paul Harris Fellow medal, Rotary International, undated (Box 253)
    - Thursday Morning Round Table, Syracuse University, undated; certificate of appreciation (Box 251)
    - "Impossible People" workshop, undated; certificate of completion (Box 251)
    - International Hall of Fame for Adults and Continuing Education, undated; medal (Box 253)
    - Unidentified medal, undated; medal with laurel leaves and engraved with Dr. Charters' name (Box 251)
  - Awards and certificates, Margaret Charters
    - American Council on Consumer Interests, 1998; 2 certificates of appreciation (Box 251)
    - Marjorie Dowdell Fortitude Award, Delta Sigma Theta Sorority, 2001; plaque (Box 253)
  - Biographical material
    - c.v.'s and resumes, most are undated but they appear to span ANC's entire career, from the 1960s to about 1996 (Box 251)
    - Syracuse University, 1950; 1959; faculty information (Box 251)
    - University of British Colombia, faculty information (Box 251)
    - University of Chicago, 1946; faculty information (Box 251)
    - Miscellaneous, statements, summaries, notes, etc. (Box 251)
  - Biographical material, personal (by ANC)
    Compiled by ANC, these are extensive and detailed descriptions covering all aspects of his life, both personal and professional. Information includes residences, hobbies, charity work, family, military service, board memberships, etc. Some pages have been redacted for sensitive information.
    - Undated early versions, 2 folders; probably all from before 1993 or 1994 (Box 251)
    - Dated versions, 1993; 1996,; 1998 (Box 251)
    - Dated versions, 1999-2001; 2004-2005; 3 folders (Box 254)
  - Calendars, desk calendars and pocket calendars, sometimes multiple per year; loose handmade calendar sheets
    - Calendars, 1971-1975; 6 folders (Box 254)
    - Calendars, 1976-1979; 6 folders (Box 255)
    - Calendars, 1979-1985; 8 folders (Box 256)
    - Calendars, 1986-1989; 5 folders (Box 257)
    - Calendars, 1990-1997; 9 folders (Box 258)
    - Calendars, 1998-2014; undated; 11 folders (Box 259)
  - Caricature of ANC, 1957; crayon, artist unknown (Box 259)
  - Charters, Louisa, 1925; 1932; material pertaining to her membership in the Order of the Eastern Star (Oversize 4)
  - Chicago, circa 1945-1948; 5 folders; programs, souvenirs, brochures, fliers, ticket stubs, and other ephemera from hockey, baseball, operas, concerts, plays, museums, etc.; includes White Sox programs and ticket stubs, Roy Rogers and Dale Evans programs, Chicago Opera, etc. (Box 260)
  - Clippings
    - Alexander Charters, 1964-1999; 2003-2007,; 2014,; undated; 6 folders; includes 1983 Learbury ad in which ANC appears as Santa Claus (Box 261)
    - Family, 1970; 1972,; 1982,; 1993,; 2003,; undated; Margaret, David, Lou Anne, others (Box 261)
    - British royal family, 1939; 1951,; 1953 (Box 261)
    - United Nations (Box 261)
    - Miscellaneous, includes some about Syracuse University, adult education (Box 261)
    - Full newspapers, 1936; 1962,; 1964; Clearwater [Florida] Sun, 21 Oct 1962; Drumheller Mail, 28 Oct 1964; Syracuse Post-Standard, 5 and 6 Aug 1964 (President Johnson dedicates Newhouse); Vancouver Daily Province 21 May 1936 (special Golden Jubilee Supplement); Vancouver Times, 17 Sep 1964 (Oversize 2)
  - Collectibles, lists, correspondence about, receipts, etc.
    - Coins (Box 260)
    - Postcards (Box 260)
    - Stamps, 2 folders (Box 260)
      See also London, 1981
  - Cunard cruise, RMS Queen Elizabeth, Feb 1968; includes 2 photographs, first class passenger list, menu signed by Commodore Marr (Box 260)
  - "Farm Family Living" booklets by Margaret MacNaughton, 3 volumes; Nicolet County, Quebec; Lanark County, Ontario; Southeastern Saskatchewan (Box 260)
  - Genealogical material, Charters, Ferguson, Hotrum, Kern, McClameroch, McLandsborough, Mealey, Ralston, and Smith; includes booklet "The Charters Family of Canada"; clipping of ANC's aunt Margaret (Charters) MacCrimmon and husband Walter Angus MacCrimmon's 50th anniversary; poem "dictated by Margaret 1917"; bookplates from Werrett W. Charters' library with Charters family crest; etc. (Box 262)
  - Guest book, possibly from Cape Cod house? Only 2 pages written in. (Oversize 1)
  - Letters of recommendation, 1939-1941; 2003 (Box 262)
  - London, 1981; 3 folders; brochures, fliers, maps, souvenir booklets, theatre programs, menus, timetables, etc.; includes stamps (Box 262)
  - London, 1986; 1991 (Box 262)
  - Photographs, personal, Family and personal photographs are filed first, followed by those related to professional occasions. A few photographs may also be found in the correspondence-subject files series, under the relevant person or organization (e.g., photographs of Sam Brightman's visits to Syracuse and Cape Cod are filed under his name).
    - [Album I], circa 1920-1940; family photographs, many annotated on back with names and dates (Oversize 3)
    - [Album II], circa 1939-1947; family photographs, many annotated on back with names and dates (Oversize 4)
    - [Album III], circa 1947-1951; family photographs, many annotated on back with names and dates (Oversize 4)
    - Great-grandparents, David and Janet (Ferguson) Charters, 1892; 1895; 2 folders (Box 263)
    - Great-grandparents, Patrick and Eliza (Phibbs) Meally (Box 263)
    - Grandparents, Alexander Maxwell and Mary Anne (Meally) Charters, 1908; 1927,; undated; includes photographs of their children, Werrett, Allen, Clifford, and Margaret (Box 263)
    - Grandparents, Nathaniel and Susan (Ralston) Kern, circa 1925; undated (Box 263)
    - Parents, Alexander Allen and Louisa Magdalena (Kern) Charters, 1890; 1900,; 1917-1918,; 1945,; 1964[?],; 1980,; undated; includes photographs of ANC as a child and of his sister Jean (Box 263)
    - ANC, college graduation (Box 263)
    - ANC, portraits, circa 1943-2014; 2 folders; formal or semiformal portrait photographs; most are undated (Box 263)
    - ANC, wedding, 1952 (Box 263)
    - ANC, family portraits, formal and semiformal portraits of children, grandchildren, family groups, etc. (Box 263)
    - ANC, family, miscellaneous, 1932-2001; undated; 4 folders (Box 263)
    - Margaret Charters, 1948; 2000,; 2002,; undated; ANC's wife; includes formal portrait shots, informal family photos, college class reunion (Box 264)
    - "Charter_tour" DVD [charters_074], 2 copies; contains several hundred family photographs (jpg format), some with accompanying html pages; printout of index page and file listing included in folder (Box 264)
    - Charters, Werret W. (uncle), 1901; 1919,; 1924,; 1934,; 1943,; 1952,; 2001,; undated; also wife Jessie Charters, Richard Lyon family; includes photo inscribed "The Old Earth works of 1812-1814 on Queenston Heights...to W.W.C."; photo of King George and Queen Mary inscribed to W. W. C. from "Dealey" (Box 264)
    - Charters family graves, Hagersville, 1985 (Box 264)
    - Cougheys, undated; appear to be late 19th or early 20th century; one has four generations of Coughey women (Box 264)
    - MacCrimmons, ANC's aunt, Margaret Belle, married Walter Angus MacCrimmon; includes their children Mary, Maxwell, Margaret (known as Jean), and Wallace; Betty jean Runcie (Box 264)
    - MacNaughtons, circa 1970?; wedding of Mark MacNaughton (Box 264)
    - Cape Cod, 1985; 2000-2001,; undated; some have water damage (Box 264)
      See also Professional: Brightman, Sam.
    - China and Russia, 1983; "People to People" trip; includes group photo and some printed material relating to the organization (Box 264)
    - "D. D. Division H. M. C. S. Kings" ship's officers, 20 Feb 1943; group photo of ship's officers; commanding officer Capt. A. M. Hope, RCN (Oversize 8)
    - Drumheller visit, undated; includes some printed material, e.g. a "Badlands Buffet" cookbook and fold-out panoramic photo (Box 264)
    - Fort Bliss, 1981; "Bill in Army"; water damage (Box 264)
    - Hagersville, well digger, before 1908; accompanying caption reads "Well-digger Hagersville Alexander Maxwell (Grandpa) before 1908" (Oversize 4)
    - Hagersville, miscellaneous, circa 1900; includes one inscribed "Hagersville Indian Reservation 1899" and "Clifford in Hagersville" (Box 264)
    - Kenya safari, 1976 (Box 264)
    - Rosedale, B.C., 1979; ANC's childhood home; includes letter from Alta Blakely, wife of Robert Blakely, who evidently took the photos (Box 264)
    - South Korea, 1999 (Box 264)